George Ord Collection 1831-1864 Mss.B.Or2
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Letter to George Ord, May 20, 1845; Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885
    Copy. Refers to a partridge. Mentions Col. Lewis and Peale’s Museum. Refers to engravings of animals.
  - Letter to George Ord, May 28, 1845; Brown, David Paul, 1795-1872
    Brown would like to rent office space below Athenaeum.
  - Letter to George Ord, June 4, 1845; Brown, David Paul, 1795-1872
    Brown decided not to rent office space below Athenaeum.
  - Letter to George Ord, July 3, 1845; Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885
    Copy. Regarding planned breakup of organization under which remnant of Wilkes expedition is working. Refers to Dr. Pickering.
  - Letter to George Ord, July 7, 1845; Humphreys, A. A., (Andrew Atkinson), 1810-1883
    Requests forwarding of packages.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Oct. 24, 1845; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Economic and political aspects. Prince of Canino.
  - Letter to Titian Ramsey Peale, Dec. 21, 1845; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Copy. APS is sued for the executors of Dunn for a debt of $10,000. Ord is thinking of retiring as treasurer.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Feb. 22, 1846; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. The Canada goose. Thinks Cuvier ventured beyond his depth in his Regne Animal. Sale of Philadelphia museum.
  - Letter to George Ord, May 1, 1846; Tidyman, Philip, d. 1850
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, May 24, 1846; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Mentions Sir Charles Menteath; Charles Bonaparte; Titian Peale; Peale museum. U.S. at war with Mexico.
  - Letter to George Ord, Sep. 20, 1846; Sartori, John B.
    Sends four pieces of fixed mercury for experiment.
  - Letter to George Ord, August 18, 1847; Darlington, William, 1782-1863
    About the assertion that the potato had been introduced into England from Virginia by Walter Raleigh. Refers to Asa Gray.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Feb. 10, 1848; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Prof. Wagner's criticism of Waterton's Essays. Has resigned as librarian and treasurer of the A.P.S.; criticism of certain members.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Wakefield, England, July 23, 1848; 10-3/4x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    A.L.S. 4p.,add. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. New Post-Office regulations. Would try to ship bull-frogs if possible. Political situation in Paris: comments on republics. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Sept. 23, 1848; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Waterton's lawsuit over alkali. Titian Peale made assistant examiner in the Patent Office. Reasoning power of animals.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Dec. 17, 1848; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    A.L.S. 4p., add. Nuisance of unpleasant odors from nearby soap and candle manufactory. Political situation in Rome. Excitement caused by news of gold in California.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, March 4, 1849; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Owner of soap and candle manufactory indicted. Gold rush. Ord's birthday. Mentions Charles Bonaparte and Agassiz.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, April 30, 1849; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Emigration to California begins to slacken. Political situation in Italy. Charles Bonaparte and Titian Peale convinced that several of Audubon's birds were "fictitious (?) representations."
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Sept. 3, 1849; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Audubon's Quadrupeds. Charles Bonaparte. Marie Monk of the "Awful disclosures." Crops abundant.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Scarborough, England, Oct. 22, 1849; 10-1/2x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Business. Friendly letter. Refers to C[harles] B[onaparte?].
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Feb. 18, 1850; 10-1/2x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. His trial against a common nuisance. California fever for gold. Concerning the "so-called" wooley horse-a forgery.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, May 5, 1850; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    A.L.S. 3p. and add. Ord's illness. Return of the Pope to the Eternal City; Italian situation. Desires news of Charles B[onaparte]. Titian Peale still in Patent Office.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, July 8, 1850; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Waterton's accident. Gold in California. Ord's ill health. Audubon.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Aug. 11, 18, 1850; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Bonaparte's part in conspiracy against the Papal government. Garibaldi in U.S. British association for the advancement of science; similar association in U.S.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Oct. 6, 1850; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    A.L.S. 4p., add. His mind somewhat below par. American politics. Charles Bonaparte's collection now in possession of the Academy of natural sciences. Mentions Wilson, Owen, Audubon, and Titian Peale.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Aug. 24, 1851; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Maria Monk's"Awful disclosures" a tissue of falsehoods. Excitement due to recent events in Cuba.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Oct. 13, 1851; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 3p. and add. The cuckoo and its young, End to invasion of Cuba. Preparations, being made for arrival of Kossuth. The Crystal Palace.
  - Letter to Titian Ramsey Peale, Jan. 27, 1852; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Ord elected president of Academy of Natural Sciences in Philadelphia.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], May 13, 1852; 10-1/2x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning hybrids. Emigration, especially from Ireland. Kossuth and his fund raising. Squirrels placed in the parks.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Oct. 7, Oct. 8, 1852; 10-1/2x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 5p.and end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Rattlesnakes. Concerning Audubon and his death. Was honored by Charles Bonaparte in Paris. Refers to T.R.Peale.
  - Letter to Titian Ramsey Peale, Dec. 4, 1852; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Refers to Peale’s unpublished book on the Wilkes’ expedition.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Dec. 12, 1852; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 2p. and add. Has had influenza. Cuba situation settled. Mentions Charles Bonaparte.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], April 17, 1853; 10-3/4x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. His health. Current craze for lecturing, and sends greetings from one lecturer Thackeray. Refers to Lea's house burning. Coments on Charles Bonaparte's rise in the world.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, June 26, 1853; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 2p. and add. Emigration from Europe. Mentions Charles Bonaparte and Padre Gavazzi.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, July 31, 1853; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Railroad travel in U.S. Mrs. Stowe's "Uncle Tom's Cabin." New York Crystal Palace. Mentions Gavazzi, Achille, Kossuth, Prof. Wilson, Sir Charles Lyell, and Lord Elsemere.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, March 19, 1854; 10-3/4x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. His health. Crimean War news: his ideas on the war.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Dec. 7, 1854; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Destruction of Peale's museum; dispersal of specimens and portraits.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Aug. 22, 1858; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Marvels at speed of communication; transmarine telegraph completed. Reported death of Sir William Jardine. Monument to Alexander Wilson.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], April 3, 1859; 10-3/4x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Natural history. Comments on dictionaries in England and the U.S. Refers to proposed monuments for Wilson and Latham. Friendly letter. Refers to academy of natural sciences.
  - Letter to George Ord, May 27, 1859
    Walton Hall, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. On war in Europe and foreign affairs. Gorilla. Frosty weather destroyed fruits and vegetables, but summer birds are here.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], March 4, 1860; 10-3/4x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Describes his ageing self. Story of John Brown. Free Negroes in Philadelphia. Mesmerism in vogue and proffered experiments by members of the APS.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Wakefield, England, June 3, 1860; 10-3/4x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Has been ill. Is failing so badly that he forgets familiar names and the spelling of simple words. Knows nothing of the young doctor who, he presumes, graduated from pennsylvania.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Nov. 29, 1860; 11-1/4x9-1/2; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence) Formerly B Or2.1. Turner on cuckoos, and Ord's ideas on the subject. Italian politics and Lincoln in the White House.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], March 10, 1861; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 4p. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning Italy. Secession of the Southern States and his belief they will fall of their own weight and lack of funds
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, June 2, 1861; 11-1/4x9-1/2; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Civil war started. Finances of both North and South and predictions of dire disaster for the South.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], July 21, 1861; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning Du Chaillu and his stories of Africa and the gorilla. Du Chaillu in the U.S. and John Cassin's comments on him in the Academy of natural sciences. Civil war.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Oct. 20, 1861; 11-1/4x9-1/2; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning Du Chaillu and his work on gorillas. Concerning J.D.Hunter's work on the Indian: his claims to have preceeded Lewis and Clark. Conversation with Sir J. Franklin over Hunter's work. Refers to the Academy of natural sciences and Cuvie and Cass.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Dec. 1, 1861; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. His opinion of Du Chaillu. Cass on Hunter and Du Chaillu, plus a story of an Iroquois claiming to be the lost Dauphin. cass comments on Sir John Franklin and Hunter. Fire in charches in Philadelphia.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], April 20, 1862; 10-3/4x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning the Civil War. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], July 27, 1862; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Monument to Wilson. News of local events. Has met some Scotsmen and read of Scotland recently.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Aug. 4, 1862; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Asks him to forward a letter to Sir James Menteith. His health. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Nov. 3, 1862; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. His health. Civil War: England should not aid the South.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Jan. 18, 1863; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Ill again. Concerning T.R.Peale. Civil War. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, March 11, 1863; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Friendly letter. Surprised at the marriage of his son. News of friends in Philadelphia.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Wakefield, Eng., May 23, 1863; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 3p.and add.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. His health. Civil war. Friendly letter. Glad Edmund is married.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Aug. 23, 1863; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. News of his health. Friendly letter. Civil war news.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Oct. 24, 1863; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. News of the war. European events.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Dec. 19, 1863; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Compares British outrages in Japan with Civil War news of New Orleans. Concerning J.E.Gray.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], March 20, 1864; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. His health. Increase in use of tobacco and its injurious effects. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], May 8, 1864; 11-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Friendly letter. Garibaldi and Italy. News of the war.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], July 17, 1864; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Friendly letter. Illness and death of Stout.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Walton Hall, Eng., Sept. 25, 1864; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Death of Stout and his other friends. News of the war. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Oct. 2, 1864; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Harvests in the U.S. News of the war.